#### Contact

9999233198 (Home) nikunj.kumar.singh@gmail.co m

www.linkedin.com/in/nikunj-kumar-singh-21557b114 (LinkedIn)

### Top Skills

Predictive Analytics Machine Learning Logistic Regression

### Languages

English (Native or Bilingual) Hindi (Native or Bilingual)

### Certifications

Data Analytics Using R
Linear Regression and Modeling
Customer Analytics
Analytics For All
Mastering Data Analysis in Excel

# Nikunj Kumar Singh

Analytics Specialist at TransOrg Analytics | Data Science | Ex AbsolutData Analytics

South Delhi

## Summary

Experienced Analytics professional with close to 3 years of experience in Analytics Consulting/Data Science using Machine Learning and Statistical Modeling Techniques. Worked on Predictive modeling (Propensity models, Churn models, etc.), Optimization Algorithms, Market-mix modeling, Text Analytics, etc. to solve complex business problems, and providing valuable insights to the clients

Domains: BFSI/Finance, Telecom, FMCG/CPG, Education, Sports, Food Retail, Hospitality

Tools Used: R, Python, VBA, SQL, Excel, AWS, Spark, Hive

# Experience

TransOrg Analytics Analytics Specialist June 2019 - Present (1 year 3 months) Gurgaon, Haryana, India

Worked on Churn propensity models, Market-mix modeling, Demand Forecasting for major Indian clients in the domain of Food Retail, CPG/FMCG, and hospitality. Leveraged machine learning and statistical techniques for solving complex business problems. Mentored and took training sessions on Linear & Logistic Regression, R, Python, Advanced Excel for freshers.

Absolutdata Analytics Business Analyst November 2017 - May 2019 (1 year 7 months) Gurgaon, India

Part of the Marketing Analytics team. Worked on the following projects:

1) Propensity Models: Worked for a major BFSI client to identify the top customers who would respond to the marketing campaigns for their products

by building response models using machine learning techniques like XGBoost, LightGBM, Random Forest, Naive Bayes, etc.

Segmented the customers into different groups based on their product usage using K-means clustering and RFM to understand the different types of customer segments and target them accordingly.

- 2) Pricing Decisions: Developed a suite of web-based applications on R shiny for a telecom giant in Africa to answer complex business questions pertaining to their pricing decisions. Conceptualized and implemented an elegant Mixed-Integer Linear Optimization (MILP) solution to determine competitive market prices. Also devised and formulated algorithms for calculation of indices for gauging Customer Price Sensitivity (CPI).
- 3) Text Analytics: Theme/Topic Classification and Theme Level Sentiment Analysis by leveraging NLP and advanced Text Analytics libraries in Python.
- 4) Market Mix-Modeling: Worked for a major FMCG/CPG client in helping the client to understand the factors driving the sales and evaluating the performance of various marketing activities. Calculated the ROIs for these marketing activities and thus optimize the spends for the future based on the What-If Scenarios.
- 5) Sports Analytics: Conceptualized an algorithm similar to the ICC Rating System based on the performance of the cricket players in different formats.

## Education

Harcourt Butler Technological Institute, Kanpur Bachelor of Technology (B.Tech.), Chemical Technology (2013 - 2017)

Suraj Bhan DAV Public School, New Delhi 12, Science · (2010 - 2012)

St Mary's Convent Sr. Secondary School, Dhampur High School · (1998 - 2010)